foreign okay so
okay so
i have one subject
that was to do with you know these five
reflections that are given for
layperson and monk alike it's the first
four to do with
recollecting that i'm subject to
aging not gone beyond aging subject to
illness not going beyond illness subject
to
death and that i will be separated from
all that's dear to me but now my
question is particularly
in regard to the last one which says
i am the owner of my actions heir to my
actions born of my actions
born of my actions
akin to my actions and my actions are my
shelter [Music]
and so i recently
heard that
um explained in a way that surprised me
a little bit because it was sort of as a
particularly buddhist
reflection on
you know something that would have to be
taken on faith that
that
you know your
if you do good good things will happen
to you in the future and it's kind of an
encouragement and i hadn't seen it in that way um
and i hadn't seen it in that way um
so
i was wondering if you could talk about
the extent to which
this type of reflection
and maybe karma and more generally is
something that is directly
visible um
um
well yeah it's definitely
much uh goes deeper than just uh
you know do good and good will come to
you especially like if
especially paired with all the other
reflections that are quite um direct and
acute you know everything that is there
will become otherwise and so on
that's not uh that's not a type of
reflection that the wood would just give
to a casual lay person
and he would give to a casual a person i'll
he would give to a casual a person i'll
do good then you'll be reborn in heaven
so since this whole thing about karma is
paired with such uh
direct instructions of reflection with
how to approve the ownership and so on
means it's on the same level so
and as the suit to say basically every
as the suit to say basically every
action is intention
so
anything that comes out of your
intention is your karma
so that's why
you need to really
understand and take on the weight of it
just on the level of intentions because
see people think i'm not doing any bad
karma because you know i'm not killing
i'm not stealing yes that's true by body
but how about speech how about the mind
how about speech how about the mind
and given that now we're talking about
the reflections that are directly
relevant to the practice you know like
i'm subject to aging death sickness
everything that's there will change okay
time is short i'm running out of time i
better do something about
in the same sense karma relates on that
same level
if it's taken on the level of your
intention the weight of it so i am the
owner of my actions means okay so each
time i intend
even by thought to do something
wholesome i i will be the owner of that
that will be the sort reason that i'm
still not uprooting
the you know suffering on account of losing
you know suffering on account of losing
what is there to me or suffering or kind
of losing health or life and so on
so that's the uh yeah it's a very it's a
very direct very acute and very
unpleasant reflection
because when also probably the subtlest
you can you know even
even somebody who doesn't want to see
with some effort you can see the subject
being subject to aging to sickness to
death you need to sort of you know dwell
on it until it sinks in
but taking on the weight of karma on the
level of your intentions
and these mental choices that people
don't really feel like it doesn't feel
like a big deal well you need to start
regarding it as a big deal if you want
to be truly free and completely free
even that very first one i am the owner
of my actions i mean i nobody else owner
of what i do in the sense like
i can't re i cannot put it on anybody
else there is nothing nothing else
that i can sort of blame or kind of
i can sort of blame or kind of
nobody can come in between nobody can
take part of it on you know we can
always it's all it's because of this or
because of that or oh well you know yes
some of it is my fault but some of it is
therefore as far as your intentions
are concerned and the results of your
actions so as far as samsara is
concerned it's all on you whatever you
do it's only on you
so there's an excuse
sort of
oh it was a very difficult external
circumstance yeah well like they would
have said even if the highway robbers
are chopping your limbs if you have the
thoughts of hate you are not you are the
one who hasn't freed yourself
it doesn't matter what they do
it doesn't matter what choices well it
matters for them not for you
so yeah it needs to be taken in that
absolute absolute sense absolute sense
and
and that part too like i am the air of
my actions paired with the others
i was thinking it's actually quite
heavy quite important
as in
this situation that i'm currently in
that is a you know danger subject to all
of these things all these liabilities
that's actually something that is
already on me somehow because of the
actions yeah because of these actions
that i'm not free from
and i'm not free from them because i've
been avoiding responsibility for them
so in order to free myself first i need
to take on the full weight of no no no
it's on me
i'm the owner of my actions i am the
heir to them whatever i do the action
the results of this action so there is
nothing to it i really need to take the
full responsibility
and that takes
even more sinking in than the previous
reflections because it doesn't feel like
it's your fault
it doesn't feel like it's your
responsibility he doesn't feel the
weight he doesn't feel heavy like when
you have these little thoughts of desire
and intentions and delights and so on
it's just these fleeting little things
most of the time i don't have that but
doesn't matter
you need to take it in a serious sense
whereby the buddha said yeah if you you
know if you if you if you're sort of
covered in mud and dirt
uh
you know removing a little bit doesn't
doesn't mean much because you're all
still absolutely covered in filth but
now imagine you're completely clean you
have a pure white cloth one tiny little
stain will stand out will be a big deal
will be visible from every angle because
everything else is clean so that's the
point if you have been practicing to the
point of
you know subject to aging sickness death
everything is there to me if you've been
enduring it violently contemplating and
understanding it then yeah you you will
realize the weight even of these little
fleeting thoughts and intentions that
you do welcome that you do accept that
you do sort of
choose to engage with at least mentally
sometimes verbally sometimes maybe
physically but
point is okay so i am not uprooting the
main reason that i am liable to all
these things that i've been
contemplating beforehand
by engaging in this oh i am maintaining
these this suffering that i am still
subject to yeah
because yeah listen more generally
karma is
often
taken as something that sort of
yeah you really just have to take it on
faith and there's no way you can
apply it directly to the practice
and that's because people confuse
that's because people confuse
the understanding with
workings of karma
they confuse that with understanding the
nature of action
and those are two separate things but
people think that aha if i understand
how karma works i thus understood what
karma is
and that's not the case
so when the buddha said if you try to
understand the workings of karma you
would meet only madness or distraction
there is not but then on many other
occasions he said he understood kama he
understood the nature of action
the root of it and uprooted it so those
are two different things if people are
not aware of that they will then sort of
approach understanding of the nature of
kama through just collecting information
about the workings of karma and and
repercussions of kama and so on and that
has nothing to do with it
yeah and if you understand the nature of
karma then you realize that the workings
of it are totally irrelevant exactly it
doesn't matter which way it works
because you're free from it the only
reason you were concerned with the
workings is because you knew you were
not free
you were under its pressure under its
control and he was unpleasant and he was
painful i think a problem with the idea that
i think a problem with the idea that
it's something that is sort of a
yeah thing that is just or maybe you take it
thing that is just or maybe you take it
on faith maybe you get the results or
not and not seeing it on that direct
and not seeing it on that direct
level
is that it sort of prevents you from
seeing that
well yeah like you just said this
well you won't realize the depth of it
yeah so it's just going to stay on the
surface and find and again it's see the
misunderstanding in that way
results in kind of you obviously sooner
or later going to think that okay yeah
you fulfill that requirement because i
do think about my karma i do good and
you know good will come to me so that's
what the buddha meant full stop
but actually you realize if you were to
then consider what if it meant even more
and start pushing it for further and you
come to realize it's the weight of your
own intentional like responsibility
behind your intentions and choices by
mind then you realize okay yeah so if i
then you realize okay yeah so if i
actually upload it on that level
then i have truly sort of
uh freed myself
from common in that sense
and you can even see how
you know this the
the situation you're in now the ways
that things have the suffering the way that
things have the suffering the way that
suffering hits you
is kind of
quite directly a result of the way that
you have been acting and the things that
you've been getting no it's not
necessarily the immediate result
but it's certainly yeah like
if you keep yourself just some mundane
example if you keep yourself unfit and
unhealthy you will be more exposed or rather even
you will be more exposed or rather even
the minimal exposure to elements would
be much more painful much harder to
endure much more overwhelming much more
bothersome because the mind hasn't been developed
because the mind hasn't been developed
in this sense the body hasn't been
developed so the voice is the same when
the mind hasn't been developed and the
mind has not practiced sensory strength
in regards to desire in regard to acting
out a will ill will every little thing
will then provoke you every little thing
will induce passion and pressure and
pain because yeah it proliferates the more
because yeah it proliferates the more
you give into it the wilder the more you
allow the wild animal to run free the
wilder it will become
i can illustrate maybe if the an example
that occurred for me recent not not that
occurred for me recent not not that
recently but a few months ago
i was um
in
seclusion at one point and at one point
my mind was just full of those thoughts
of
unwholesome things that i had done or in
wholesome ways i've behaved in the past
that i regretted which was unpleasant
and uh previously i would have thought that
uh previously i would have thought that
i would have had to
try not to have these thoughts and try
to stop them
at that point uh fortunately enough i
had gained a little bit more wisdom so i was
gained a little bit more wisdom so i was
not sort of trying to stop them just
trying to enjoy them but at one point
it occurred to me a suta that i had read
ages ago
it was one of these where the buddha
sees a monk
just sitting in the forest or something and
sitting in the forest or something and
he's
and it says
this monk
was experiencing sharp piercing feelings
on account of his past wrong actions
yeah and i remember at the time when i
read that i had sort of thought of it as
of some kind of magical feeling physical
torture spirits or something yeah and
then i was like wait a second
here i am feeling unpleasant feelings on
account of my past actions and it said
in the surah he's patiently enduring
them yeah so here okay i have to
patiently enjoy them if you can't see it
on that kind of direct
my mind
is kind of the results accumulation of
these past things and it was like simply
you see like a possibility
of regret
is another result of your action
of any action
so that's why you know the wood often
talks about blamelessness and and doing
the actions they will not be
blame-worthy because
if they're blame-worthy
sooner or later if you know if you don't
perpetually distract yourself up until
the moment you die
the mind will become aware and the
regret and the weight of it will have to
come and it will be unpleasant and he
could have been avoided if you didn't
act in the first place yeah yeah yeah
and but again it's like people regard as
the parker the result of the action as
some sort of again mystical retribution
that comes later in time
simply means result
so in the same sense now i say can you
get up and pass me that bottle
everything that happens as a result of
that action will be the result of that
action from my point of view
getting the bottle of water you said
maybe you get upset because i asked you
something i didn't ask you nicely that
would be the result from my point of
view of my action that is the my vipaka
because it resulted now all i can do i
can't control those results
but i can control or make sure that my
initial action
was not rooted in greed aversion i
didn't make you do it to humiliate you
or because i hate you or something like
that then it doesn't matter
then it doesn't matter
which way it results i know that the
origins of it were not rooted in
unwholesome roots and that's all you can
do and that's all you need to do
then any vipaka that comes it's not mine
and it doesn't pertain to me and it
cannot make the mind turn against itself
because again you have you have ceased
to provide
that kind of unwholesome connection of
of lust aversion anger distraction
so
yeah yeah that's that's exactly what
what parker is
you don't need to wait for future
rebirths and so on to see the results of
what you've been doing you are the
result of what you've been doing your
habits are the results of what you've
been doing
and each time you choose to engage with
the results of what you've been doing
that's your new action at that given
time so it's not determinism it's not that
so it's not determinism it's not that
you you can't stop it every single time
you choose to accept those results of
your actions as valid as whatever else
an act out of them that's your current
choice they then perpetuate those results
they then perpetuate those results
exactly like that was
you know at that even time
of that kind of little story i was
telling is
i really kind of realized okay this is
the point you know this is why
now the thing is not to try to get rid
of these thoughts or try to kind of do
something else on account of them run
away from them the point is to not feed
this same thing that has given me now
this pain yeah and then immediately you
know and then the mind will say yeah but what
and then the mind will say yeah but what
if this pain
lasts you know for a long time doesn't
matter what if you last for a year
doesn't matter what if for the rest of
my life
i don't get a moment of peace when i
can't do this fine
still i won't act out of it
because the mind will say that the mind
will make any of such endurances uh it
will make like it will throw the threat
of infinity at you oh this will forever
now haunt you because see you can't
change what you did
what you're gonna do now nothing i'll
endure it for as long as it takes
even if it takes lifetimes but it won't
it's an irrational sort of scare tactic
so to speak
and that's again that's what mara was
doing in the suit often would kind of
try and present you the worst case
scenario but see
you have to accept it
it's not like okay yeah mara presents me
the worst case scenario but he won't be
he might be he might be right and he
might be forever he might be for the
rest of your life that feeling will
never change you're just going to be in
petrol pain doesn't matter still you're
going to endure it on the same lab
because only by by willing to endure it forever
only by by willing to endure it forever
so to speak on that level
you will get to actually see where the
problem really is and it's not in what
you've done it's not in how long things
will last
it's not in what's happening to you it's
in your present attitude of present
craving against that discomfort
so that's where the pain is that's what
the problem is and that's why things
these things that you seemingly have to
do forever would
would uh haunt you
and be painful only because you're
resisting them here and now
but you can
at least for me it was
very um important to realize like
um important to realize like
i can endure it now because i know that
that's what i have to do like in that in
that sense and there's no confusion in
that exactly yeah and the you know
doesn't matter how
how much pressure
it kind of brings on to you you know but
this is what needs to be done and that
in itself it's quite liberating just the
knowledge of what needs to be done
correctly on the right level
because why that does not provide a
sense of relief to people it's because
they don't see what needs to be done
they assume what needs to be done they
act out of
a sense of duty what needs to be done
and how needs to be dealt with but they
don't really know and see for themselves
what needs to be done and in this case
nothing in the sense nothing directly
needs to be done you just need to endure
on account of things you've already done
or you already did
and it's it's the same whether it comes
to centrality
aversion any of the hindrances basically
when you try to pressure you and these
thoughts revolve
that's that's how you deal with them
that's how you go outside of their
domain by not you know jumping in and
trying to address them and
prevent them management manage them
justify them explain them
rationalize them psychologize them and
so on
yeah and it is i mean the same principle
for any of the hindrances like the
pressure of doubt douse sensuality any
of them
on account of how much you've been
feeding so the pain will be there of
that pressure
how much you suffer on account of that
pain basically means we'll be determining how
basically means we'll be determining how
much you you don't know what need to do
what you need to do rightly and how much
you're resisting it
that's how much you're going to suffer
in and of itself does not necessarily
mean suffering even with all the
discomfort that might bring onto you
so that would be the true end of karma
and that's why this like the um
the whole um
surmounting of the hindrances
establishing the mind in the genre it's
basically surpassing
the the domain of action in vipaka in
that sense it will you know now that
depends on every individual for how long
you have to do it but if you are doing
it rightly it will have to result in
complete removal of the slightest traces
of ownership
in regard to past
future present
doesn't matter that's why i would have
said the one who understands this he
doesn't even think anymore i am
i will be and i was in the past when he
remembers that that part of not that he
forgot what he did in the past or the
memories of the past are gone but the
sense of ownership was always maintained
in the present
through that ignorance through that lack
of knowledge through the lack of clarity
through that constant ignorant engaging
with those actions
so now he has approved to that which
means when he thinks of the past he's
not taking it up
as mine
when he has thoughts of future and
what's going to happen what he's going
to do he's not taking that up as mine
but more often than not that's too subtle
more often than not that's too subtle
for people to discern so they just tend
to default onto dismissing the past and
the future and mystifying the presence
i heard that countless numbers of times
our past is no more future is not yet
it's only the now and stuff like that
you don't even need the buddha to tell
you but you still have your memories
even if you are perpetually dismissing
the past or refraining from thinking
about the future
see that's the future idea oh i shall
sustain this idea in the future where i
will not think about the future and thus
i'll be free from the future
but that's a contradiction in terms
again so
so
whether it's the present whether it's
whether it's the past whether it's the
future they're equally present as past and as
they're equally present as past and as
future
so and that's why that's where the
problem is
here and now are you taking it up is
mine are you resisting it are you dismissing
are you resisting it are you dismissing
it are you afraid of it are you affected
by any hindrance on account of it
and if the answer is yes yeah there you
go endure it on that level don't concern
yourself with like rewriting the past or
preventing the future
just keep
keep an eye keep a watchful eye on the
doorway of your actions here and now
oh i don't know what i'm going to do but
i know what i will not do
so that way you know even
you don't have to worry about what
specific thing i might do in the future
as long as i
know what i have to keep yeah because it
doesn't matter what specific thing is
done what matters is whether it was
rooted in three diversion delusion sure
if there is no greater version illusion
certain specific things cannot be done
but that's not because you were
concerned about the specifics but
because you pulled out the roots that
they would need to grow from so that
would be the true end of karma
i think that's something probably quite
hard for
it's quite hard to understand because
it's like i think it was none of yours
that at once
intention does not imply craving which
is a very hard thing to understand there
is no craving without intention
but there is intention without craving
but if you get to see that you will be
on the way of freeing yourself from
craving yeah because as a
yeah because as a
when you start
intention equals like intention is
craving and that's i mean that's what you need
and that's i mean that's what you need
to take that full blanket responsibility
for it
i am the owner of my actions my choices
my intentions
even if you know
i didn't act out of them
okay so but have i accepted them
mentally am i delighting in them am i
resisting them at least on that mental
level to that extent you are involved
so that's that whole like the you know
learning how to do things correctly
and during mental level like you had all
these thoughts
presenting yourself trying to trap you
pull you engage you
get you to lose perspective basically
and try to deal with them specifically
but you didn't so you had to endure mind
on the level of the mind doing that
there's nothing else you would you could
have done by both you by speech they
would have addressed it on that level
except try to distract yourself but that
only has a limited success and sooner or
later it will have to run out
so and that's that's again that's
exactly what the practice is
and that's where people can spend
decades of practicing on the external
level but if they never allow things and
take responsibility for them on that
mental level on the level of mental
intention there is no practice
that is just the emulation of practice
but internally there are no there's no
proper basis established
and if you're
and if you're not doing it like that
that's when i think
if it's so common or at least that i was
thinking like this previously as well
like okay i'll just keep going and
you know keep trying at some point the
results of the practice will
come and again you can only really think like
and again you can only really think like
that if you're not fully taking
responsibility for the fact that wait
i'm not free from suffering right now
and everything that i'm doing
is
might be kind of perpetuating that or
yeah and
so then the kind of
because that's too unpleasant
the the practice the things you do are
kept on that external level at the arm's
length which then also results in you expecting
which then also results in you expecting
the results of your practice to come
from that external level
so i have all this mess in my mind oh i
can't think about it or endure it's just
you know be here now and budo and
present is here and future is not yet
and so on and then i'll just do these
motions and techniques and whatever else
i commit myself to
and then hopefully you know i'm going to
have the experience
arising as a result of it and all these
bad things in my mind will be addressed
and i will not be able to suffer anymore
and that's the pure bliss and pure
enlightenment and yeah i'm sure there were teachers in
and yeah i'm sure there were teachers in
the buddhist time they would have
advocated and advertised that
but it was quite clear that that's not
where the practice is
it's on the level of intention
wholesome unwholesome
uh and uh yeah not losing perspective in
regard to it
enduring it on that level and that's
that what he called the true tapas
the true kind of uh ascetic practice of
you know you can endure the heat the
cold the pain the torture
endure things on that level of the
thought and intention without welcoming
the lighting or resisting or trying to
get ready to justify or psychologize you
are actually purifying your mind whether
you want it or not because nobody wants
to do it on that level
and at the same time feel responsible
for it
yeah which is even worse or harder
and that and the hard thing too is like
the whether when it's about the
whether when it's about the
unwholesome and wholesome intentions
only you
can really know
another reason that it's
quite hard to
feel fully responsible for it because
you can't ask somebody else necessarily
for was it good or was it bad or when
you can to an extent but yeah in the
beginning but really ultimately you have
to know for yourself and yes
so you need to start like doing your own
digging because that's not going to just
because that's not going to just
magically reveal itself because the
entire existence is about covering it up
the centrality acting out of real will
distraction all of that has in common
the attitude of covering that very thing
up because it's unpleasant to recognize
that it's on you
it's on you
and you chose one thing you could have
chosen another either way
it's on you
so you are fully responsible whether you
want to interpret that as everything is
my fault
or or in any other way either way
responsibility is fully on you
and even say if you say for the sake of
argument's sake if you're like
practicing yeah everything is my fault
yeah everything is my fault
what's the problem with that thought why
are you resisting that thought why are
you afraid of that thought
are you panicking when you think that
are you being overwhelmed okay that's
your work cut out for you so you need to
be able to even accept that thought
because point will come when mara will
say that everything is your fault
look what you did
and there was numerous sutras in
territory when he did exactly that see
it's because of what you did
or what you wanted to do but then you
know if monks and when monks and nuns
had wisdom they could see he's like who
are you talking about
all there is is do kakami and duke are
going i'm not the owner of any of this
because i purify myself from that
dracula's ownership that has been
maintained and perpetuated through great
diversion delusion so yeah now i just
have to endure dukkha coming and going
until until it completely disappears
but it's not it's not going to be like a
like a magical kind of a finger snap
clearance instantaneously freed from all
of that no
so if you're scared of certain thoughts
that's a problem
you being
overwhelmed by fear is a problem
if you're like uh
if it's impossible for you to remain
unmoved by certain other thoughts of
like sensuality that's a problem if it's
impossible you know for you to not have
then thoughts of cruelty
thoughts of cruelty
hate anger when you're annoyed or
irritated or offended or result that's a
problem so all those things that
so all those things that
again are on the level of the mind
if they move you if they if that passion
sort of engages you and you cannot
withstand it you cannot endure it
uh you cannot but give in to it that's a
problem so that's why like you shouldn't kind of
so that's why like you shouldn't kind of
well i mustn't be thinking that no you
should be able to think whatever you
want to think
and the mind should not be able to
overwhelm you on account of that
so yes that doesn't mean you just in one
go you think everything at once
but as i said if such a thought of as it
came up in this example also that means
everything is my fault comes up well
maybe am i afraid of that doesn't matter if
am i afraid of that doesn't matter if
the answer is right or wrong what
matters is am i already trembling under
the prospect what if it is my fault yeah
but if it is maybe it is well in the way
it is
let's say like that
so the worst case scenario whatever it
is is that moving you is that
threatening you if it is to that extent
you are holding back to that extent you
are expecting shelter to come from the
world to prevent these thoughts and
circumstances from arising and that's
not going to happen or it's going to
happen only for a period of time sooner
or later it will have to change and you
will be fully exposed without a shelter
without safety
yeah because like when you say
yeah if you're not if you're
able to be moved by
any of these kind of thoughts it's a
problem but it's
it's my problem as in it's my it's my
fault even that yeah exactly that's the
fault see not like all you know what
i've done ignorantly and stuff yeah true
that's a relative fault
every time you acted out of greed or
anger and so on yeah it's a relative
fault what is the acute here and our
fault is you being moved by that and
accepting that
and and and trying to outrun it trying
to get rid of it and so on that's the
actual living fault
but it's also nice blemish yeah
and it would be then easy to kind of
think okay so i should i should not be
moved by this
yeah i should try but you can't you have
to just stop again like well again so
you can think that i should not be moved
by this okay so where was this decision
rooted in now
in the fact that i was moved by it
and the fact that it was unpleasant and
the fact that i don't want that
discomfort thus i will now decide to
never be moved by it so fundamentally
you're not really deciding to never be
moved by it you're just deciding to try
to outrun the suffering yet again
but see
you're going to be doing that every now
and then but if you do know where to
look such as you know the reasons for your
such as you know the reasons for your
actions whatever those actions and
decisions are
you will get to see okay yeah i have had
a thought of i shall not be moved by
this but at the same time i do still
have perspective that not being moved
means not acting out including with the
thought of i shall not be moved by this
and that's how you cease to be moved
so then there was a right thought it
matched your experience i shall not be
moved and i haven't been moved at will i
can be now unmoved
because the craving has been removed
needless to say of course one will be
able to see this correctly
to see this correctly
after the proper and thorough
development of the gradual training that
we so often described in many other
videos